- Mathematics began as a way to quantify our world,
to measure land,
predict the motions of planets, and keep track of commerce.
Then came a problem considered impossible.
The secret to solving it was to separate math
from the real world, to split algebra from geometry
and to invent new numbers so fanciful
they are called imaginary.
Ironically, 400 years later, these very numbers turn up
in the heart of our best physical theory of the universe.
Only by abandoning math's connection to reality
could we discover reality's true nature.
In 1494, Luca Pacioli
who is Leonardo da Vinci's math teacher publishes
"Summa de Arithmetica," a comprehensive summary
of all mathematics known in Renaissance Italy at the time.
In it, there's a section on the cubic,
any equation which today we would write as ax cubed
plus bx squared plus cx plus d equals zero.
People have been trying to find a general solution
to the cubic for at least 4,000 years,
but each ancient civilization that encountered it,
the Babylonians, Greeks, Chinese,
Indians, Egyptians, and Persians,
they all came up empty-handed.
Pacioli's conclusion is that a solution
to the cubic equation is impossible.
Now, this should be at least a little surprising,
since without the X cubed term,
the equation is simply a quadratic.
And many ancient civilizations
had solved quadratics thousands of years earlier.
Today, anyone who's passed eighth grade
knows the general solution.
It's minus b plus minus root b squared minus four ac
all over two a.
But most people just plug and chug into this formula
completely oblivious to the geometry
that ancient mathematicians used to derive it.
You know, back in those days,
mathematics wasn't written down in equations.
It was written with words and pictures.
Take, for example,
the equation x squared plus 26x equals 27.
Ancient mathematicians would think of the x squared term
like a literal square with sides of length x.
And then 26x,
well, that would be a rectangle with one side of length 26
and the other side of length x,
and these two areas together add to 27.
So how do we figure out what x is?
Well, we can take this 26x rectangle and cut it in half.
So now I have two 13x rectangles and I can position them
so the new shape I create is almost a square,
It's just missing this section down here.
But I know the dimensions of this section.
It's just 13 by 13.
So I can complete the square by adding in
a 13 by 13 square.
Now, since I've added 13-squared
or 169 to the left-hand side of the equation,
I also have to add 169
to the right-hand side of the equation
to maintain the equality.
So now I have this larger square
with sides of length X plus 13, and it is equal to 196.
Now the square root of 196 is 14.
So I know that the sides of this square have length 14,
which means X is equal to one.
Now this is a great visual way to solve a quadratic equation,
这是一种非常直观的二次方程的解法
but it isn't complete.
但它并不完整
I mean, if you look at our original equation,
如果你仔细看看原始的方程
x equals one is a solution.
x=1确实是一个解
But so is negative 27.
但是还有另一个解是x=-27
For thousands of years, mathematicians were oblivious
几千年来  数学家们都无视了
to the negative solutions to their equations
方程的负数解
because they were dealing with things in the real world,
因为他们正尝试用数学解决实际问题
lengths and areas and volumes.
长度  面积  体积
I mean, what would it mean to have a square
边长为-27的正方形在现实中能表示什么呢
with sides of length negative 27?
That just doesn't make any sense.
这完全没有意义
So for those mathematicians, negative numbers didn't exist.
因此对于当时的数学家来说  负数解并不存在
You could subtract,
你可以做减法
that is find the difference between two positive quantities,
寻找两个正数之间的差异
but you couldn't have a negative answer
但你不能得到一个为负的答案
or negative coefficients.
或者负系数
Mathematicians were so averse to negative numbers
数学家们非常厌恶负数
that there was no single quadratic equation.
以至于二次方程没有一般式
Instead, there were six different versions
而是产生了6个不同的方程
arranged so that the coefficients were always positive.
以保证所有的系数都为正
The same approach was taken with the cubic.
三次方程也采用了相同的处理方法
In the 11th century, Persian mathematician
11世纪中期  波斯数学家
奥马尔·海亚姆
identified 19 different cubic equations,
确定了19种不同的三次方程
again, keeping all coefficients positive.
同样保证所有的系数都为正
He found numerical solutions to some of them
他通过分析几何图形的交点
by considering the intersections of shapes,
找到了其中一些方程的解
like hyperbolas and circles,
例如双曲线和圆
but he fell short of his ultimate goal,
但他仍无法达到他的最终目标
a general solution to the cubic.
三次方程的一般解
He wrote,
他写道
“也许在我们之后的某个人
可以成功地解开这个问题”
400 years later and 4,000 kilometers away,
400年之后  在4000公里之外
the solution begins to take shape.
答案逐渐开始成型
希皮奥内·德尔·费罗
is a mathematics professor at the University of Bologna.
是博洛尼亚大学的一位数学教授
Sometime around 1510,
在1510年左右
he finds a method to reliably solve depressed cubics.
他找到了“弱三次方程”的通用解法
These are a subset of cubic equations
这是一类特殊的三次方程
with no X squared term.
没有二次项
So what does he do after solving a problem that has stumped
困扰了数学家们几千年的问题被他解决后
mathematicians from millennia?
他又做了什么呢
One considered impossible
一个被达芬奇的数学老师
by Leonardo da Vinci's math teacher?
认为是不可能解决的问题
He tells no one.
他缄口如瓶
See, being a mathematician in the 1500s is hard.
在16世纪  当个数学家非常难
Your job is constantly under threat
你的工作会不断受到威胁
from other mathematicians who can show up at any time
其他数学家随时都可能出现
and challenge you for your position.
然后挑战你的地位
You can think of it like a math duel.
你可以理解成一种数学决斗
Each participant submits a set of questions to the other,
每一位参与者提交一组问题给对手
and the person who solves
然后解答正确数最多的那位获胜
the most questions correctly gets the job
while the loser suffers public humiliation.
然而败者则会蒙受耻辱
As far as del Ferro knows,
据德尔·费罗所知
no one else in the world can solve the depressed cubic.
世上没有其他人能解出弱三次方程
So by keeping his solutions secret,
因此  只要他对自己的解法保密
he guarantees his own job security.
即可保证自己的研究成果不被超越
For nearly two decades, del Ferro keeps his secret.
德尔·费罗将他的秘密保守了近二十年
Only on his deathbed in 1526
直到1526年他临终前
does he let it slip to his student
他才将解法透露给了他的学生
安东尼奥·菲奥尔
Fior is not as talented a mathematician as his mentor,
菲奥尔并不像他的导师那样有才华
but he is young and ambitious.
但他年轻而且野心勃勃
And after del Ferro's death,
在德尔·费罗死后
he boasts about his own mathematical prowess
他吹嘘自己的数学能力
and specifically, his ability to solve the depressed cubic.
并且他大吹特吹  自己能解弱三次方程
On February 12, 1535,
Fior challenges mathematician
尼科洛·丰坦纳·塔尔塔利亚
who has recently moved to Fior's hometown of Venice.
Niccolo Fontana is no stranger to adversity.
As a kid, his face was cut open by a French soldier,
leaving him with a stutter.
That's why he's known as Tartaglia,
which means stutterer in Italian.
Growing up in poverty, Tartaglia is largely self-taught.
He claws his way up through Italian society
to become a respected mathematician.
Now, all of that is at stake.
As is the custom, in the challenge Tartaglia gives
a very discernment of 30 problems to Fior.
Fior gives 30 problems to Tartaglia,
all of which are depressed cubics.
Each mathematician has 40 days
to solve the 30 problems they've been given.
Fior can't solve a single problem.
Tartaglia solves all 30 of Fior's depressed cubics
in just two hours.
It seems Fior's boastfulness was his undoing.
Before the challenge came, Tartaglia learns
that Fior's claimed to have solved the depressed cubic,
but he's skeptical.
依我之见  他的能力不足以独立解出这个问题
Tartaglia writes.
But word was that a great mathematician
had revealed the secret to Fior,
which seems more plausible.
So with the knowledge that a solution to the cubic is possible,
and with his livelihood on the line,
Tartaglia sets about solving the depressed cubic himself.
To do it, he extends the idea
of completing the square into three dimensions.
Take the equation x cubed plus nine x equals 26.
You can think of x cubed
as the volume of a cube with sides of length x.
And if you add a volume of nine x, you get 26.
So just like with completing the square,
we need to add onto the cube
to increase its volume by nine x.
Imagine extending three sides of this cube out a distance y,
creating a new, larger cube with sides of length, call it z.
z is just x plus y.
The original cube has been padded out
and we can break up the additional volume into seven shapes.
There are three rectangular prisms
with dimensions of x by x by y,
and another three narrower prisms
with dimensions of x by y by y,
plus there's a cube with a volume y cubed.
Tartaglia rearranges the six rectangular prisms into one block.
One side has length three y,
the other has a length x plus y, which is z,
and the height is x.
So the volume of this shape
is its base, three yz times its height, x.
And Tartaglia realizes this volume can perfectly represent
the nine x term in the equation,
if its base is equal to nine.
So he sets three yz equals nine.
Putting the cube back together,
you find we're missing the one small y cubed block,
so we can complete the cube
by adding y cubed to both sides of the equation.
Now we have z cubed, the complete larger cube,
equals 26 plus y cubed.
We have two equations and two unknowns.
Solving the first equation for z
and substituting into the second,
we get y to the six plus 26 y cubed equals 27.
At first glance, it seems like we're now worse off
than when we started.
The variable is now raised to the power of six,
instead of just three.
However, if you think of y cubed as a new variable,
the equation is actually a quadratic,
the same quadratic that we solved by completing the square.
So we know y cubed equals one,
which means y equals one, and z equals three over y,
so z is three.
And since x plus y equals z, x must be equal to two,
which is indeed, a solution to the original equation.
And with that,
Tartaglia becomes the second human on the planet
to solve the depressed cubic.
To save himself the work of going through the geometry
for each new cubic he encounters,
Tartaglia summarizes his method in an algorithm,
a set of instructions.
He writes this down not as a set of equations
like we would today.
Modern algebraic notation wouldn't exist
for another hundred years,
but instead, as a poem.
若三次项并其后的一次项
等于某个自然数
则以该数为差值  寻甲乙两数
接着  按照惯例
甲乙之积总是会等于
一次项系数之少半  自再乘
剩余的步骤就是
甲乙开立方  得值相减
即为汝方程之未知数
在第二种情况中
三次项独立放一边
你可以走另一条路
常数项可拆为甲乙两数之和
而甲乙之积仍直接等于
一次项系数之少半  自再乘
接着  出于常识
开立方除甲并开立方除乙
得和乃汝之未知数
至于第三类计算
则与第二类联立
你若细心斟酌
可见两式之解正负相抵
我找到的方法
用起来可不慢
在一千五百三十四年
凭借无比坚实的基础
于此环海之城
Tartaglia's victory makes him something of a celebrity.
Mathematicians are desperate to learn
how he solved the cubic, especially
吉罗拉莫·卡尔达诺
a polymath based in Milan.
As you can guess, Tartaglia will have none of it.
He refuses to reveal even a single question from the competition.
But Cardano is persistent.
He writes a series of letters
that alternate between flattery and aggressive attacks.
Eventually with the promise of an introduction
to his wealthy benefactor,
Cardono manages to lure Tartaglia to Milan.
And there on March 25, 1539
Tartaglia reveals his method,
but only after forcing Cardono to swear a solemn oath
not to tell anyone the method,
not to publish it,
and to write it only in cipher.
Quote, "So that after my death,
no one shall be able to understand it."
Cardono is delighted
and immediately starts playing around with Tartaglia's algorithm.
But he has a loftier goal in mind,
a solution to the full cubic equation, including the x squared term.
And amazingly, he discovers it.
If you substitute for x,
x minus b over three a,
then all the X squared terms cancel out.
This is the way to turn any general cubic equation
into a depressed cubic,
which can then be solved by Tartaglia's formula.
Cardano is so excited to have solved the problem
that stumped the best mathematicians for thousands of years,
he wants to publish it.
Unlike his peers,
Cardano has no need to keep the solution a secret.
He makes his living not as a mathematician,
but as a physician and famous intellectual.
For him, the credit is more valuable than the secret.
The only problem is the oath he swore to Tartaglia
who won't let him break it.
And you might think this would be the end of it.
But in 1542, Cardano travels to Bologna
and there he visits a mathematician
who just happens to be the son-in-law
of one Scipione del Ferro, the man who on his deathbed,
gave the solution to the depressed cubic to Antonio Fior.
Cardano finds the solution in del Ferro's old notebook,
which is shared with him during the visit.
This solution predates Tartaglia's by decades.
So now, as Cardano sees it,
he can publish the full solution to the cubic
without violating his oath to Tartaglia.
Three years later,
Cardano publishes "Ars Magna," The Great Art,
an updated compendium of mathematics.
写就凡五载  流芳愿千年
Cardano writes a chapter with a unique geometric proof
for each of the 13 arrangements of the cubic equation.
Although he acknowledges
the contributions of Tartaglia, del Ferro and Fior,
Tartaglia is displeased, to say the least.
He writes insulting letters to Cardano,
无耻  无权无势的男人
愚蠢至极的男人
数学研究的门外汉
and CC's a good fraction of the mathematics community.
And he has a point.
To this day, the general solution to the cubic
is often called Cardano's method.
But "Ars Magna" is a phenomenal achievement.
It pushes geometrical reasoning to its very breaking point.
Literally.
While Cardano is writing "Ars Magna"
在卡尔达诺写 "Ars Magna" 这本书的时候，
he comes across some cubic equations
他发现了一些不能以正常方式解出答案的三次等式
that can't easily be solved in the usual way,
like x cubed equals 15x plus four.
比如 x³ = 15x + 4
Plugging this into the algorithm yields a solution
把这个放进算法里会算出含有负数平方根的答案。
that contains the square roots of negative numbers.
Cardano asks Tartaglia about the case,
卡尔达诺向塔尔塔利亚询问了这件事
but he evades and implies Cardano
但塔尔塔利亚回避了这个问题
is just not clever enough to use his formula properly.
并表示卡尔达诺只是并不够聪明去正确使用他的等式
The reality is Tartaglia has no idea what to do either.
真实的情况是，塔尔塔利亚也对这个问题一筹莫展
Cardano walks back through the geometric derivation
卡尔达诺回头重新看了相似问题的几何推导过程
of a similar problem to see exactly what goes wrong.
以求发现到底在哪里出现了问题
While the 3D cube slicing and rearrangement works just fine,
虽然用3D立方切片以及重新安排的方式正好能解决问题
the final quadratic completing the square step
但在解最后的那一个填满正方形的二元方程式时
leads to a geometric paradox.
发生了一个几何上的矛盾
Cardano finds part of a square that must have an area of 30,
卡尔达诺发现，正方形的面积必须是30
but also sides of length five.
但它的边长同时也必须是5
Since the full square has an area of 25,
因为这整个正方形的面积是25
卡尔达诺就必须用某种方式增加一些负面积
to complete the square,
要使这个正方形完整
Cardano has to somehow add negative area.
That is where the square roots of negatives come from,
这就是那个负平方根，亦即是负面积的概念出来的地方
the idea of negative area.
Now, this isn't the first time
现在，这不是第一次负平方根出现在数学里面
square roots of negatives show up in mathematics.
In fact, earlier in "Ars Magnae" is this problem.
实际上，这个问题在更早的《大术》中就已经出现了
Find two numbers that add to 10 and multiply to 40.
要找到相加等于10，相乘等于40的两个数
You can combine these equations into the quadratic
你可以将这些等式结合为 x² + 40 = 10x
X squared plus 40 equals 10 X.
But if you plug this into the quadratic formula,
但是如果你将这个式子代入二元方程公式
the solutions contain the square roots of negatives.
解出来的答案将含有负的平方根
The obvious conclusion is that a solution doesn't exist,
很明显，这样的解根本不会存在
which you can verify by looking at the original problem.
你可以透过重新看原题来验证这个事实
There are no two real numbers,
没有两个实数既能在相加等于10的同时，相乘等于40
which add to 10 and multiply to 40.
So mathematicians understood
所以数学家们知道
square roots of negative numbers
负数的平方根是以数学的形式告诉你这个式子没有解
were maths way of telling you there is no solution.
But this cubic equation is different.
但是这个三次等式是不一样的
With the little guessing and checking,
在使用亿点点的猜想和查证下
you can find that x equals four is a solution.
你可以发现 x = 4 是一个解
So why doesn't the approach that works for all other cubics
所以为什么能适用于其他全部立方体的方法
find the perfectly reasonable solution to this one?
不能在这个等式上求出完美的合理的解呢？
Unable to see a way forward,
因为看不到有任何的出路
Cardano avoids this case in "Ars Magna"
卡尔达诺回避了在《大术》里面的这个问题
saying the idea of the square root of negatives
并表示负数平方根的概念 「是一种取巧且不必要」
"is as subtle as it is useless".
But around 10 years later, the Italian engineer
但10年之后，意大利的工程师拉斐尔.邦贝利
Rafael Bombelli picks up where Cardano left off.
在卡尔达诺停下的地方继续研究
Undeterred by the square roots of negatives
因为对负数平方根与它们能表达的不可能几何的坚信（？）
and the impossible geometry they imply,
he wants to find a way through the mess to the solution.
他想要找到到达题解中心的道路
Observing that the square root of a negative
观察一个负数平方根
"cannot be called either positive or negative",
“既不能不能被称为正，也不能被称为负”
he lets it be its own new type of number.
他定义这种数为一种新数类
Bombelli assumes the two terms in Cardano's solution
邦贝利设想在卡尔达诺的解中的这两个术语
can be represented as some combination
能以某种组合普通数及这种新数的方式呈现
of an ordinary number and this new type of number,
which involves the square root of negative one.
这能将负数平方根包含在解里面
And this way, Bombelli figures out
透过这种方式，邦贝利发现
that the two cube roots in Cardano's equation
这两个在卡尔达诺等式的立方根
are equivalent to two
等价于两个加或减那个负数平方根
plus or minus the square root of negative one.
So when he takes the final step and adds them together,
这样当他执行那最后一步，将它们加起来之后
the square roots cancel out,
这个平方根就被消掉了
leaving the correct answer, four.
流下了正确的答案，4
This feels nothing short of miraculous.
这种方式感觉没有任何的奇思妙想（？）
Cardano's method does work,
卡尔达诺的方式的确能解决问题
but you have to abandon the geometric proof
但你必须要抛弃在第一步生成几何证明
that generated it in the first place.
Negative areas, which make no sense in reality,
负平面，这个在真实世界上没有任何意义的东西
must exist as an intermediate step
是一定得作为一个在通往答案的中间步骤而存在的
on the way to the solution.
Over the next hundred years, modern mathematics takes shape.
在下一个百年中，现代数学开始成型
In the 1600s,
在17世纪
弗朗索瓦·韦达
introduces the modern symbolic notation for algebra,
引入了代数的现代符号标记法
ending the millennia-long tradition
结束了千年之久的将解决数学问题抽象成
of math problems as drawings and wordy descriptions.
既要画画又要很啰嗦描述问题的习惯（？）
Geometry is no longer THE source of truth.
几何学不再是真相的来源
勒内·笛卡尔
makes heavy use of the square roots of negatives,
经常使用负数平方根
popularizing them as a result.
使它们被广泛认知
And while he recognizes their utility,
在他识别它们的效用的时候
he calls them imaginary numbers, a name that sticks,
他将它们称为虚数，一个固定的名字（？）
which is why Euler later introduces the letter i
这也是为什么在之后欧拉将字幕i引入来表示这个负平方根
to represent the square root of negative one.
When combined with regular numbers,
当虚数与实数结合在一起的时候
they form complex numbers.
它们形成了复数
The cubic led to the invention of these new numbers
三次方程促进了这些新数的发明
and liberated algebra from geometry.
并把代数从几何中解放出来
By letting go of what seems like the best description of reality,
扬弃了这些可见可感、
the geometry you can see and touch,
表面上最符合现实的几何描述后
you get a much more powerful and complete mathematics
得到了一个适于求解真实问题的数学体系
that can solve real problems.
它更加强大和完整
And it turns out the cubic is just the beginning.
实际上三次方程仅仅是一个开始
In 1925,
在1925年
埃尔文·薛定谔
is searching for a wave equation
正在寻找一个波动方程
that governs the behavior of quantum particles
以此描述粒子行为的量子性
building on de Broglie's insight that matter consists of waves.
基于德布罗意  有关波的本质的深刻见解
He comes up with one of the most important
他提出了物理学史上最重要而著名的方程之一
and famous equations in all of physics,
the Schrödinger equation.
薛定谔方程
And featured prominently within it is i,
这个方程最主要的特点是它含有 i
the square root of negative one.
负一的平方根
While mathematicians have grown accustomed to imaginary numbers,
当数学家已经习惯于虚数的存在时
physicists have not
物理学家还没有
and are uncomfortable seeing it show up
虚数在这些基本理论中的出现
in such a fundamental theory.
给他们带来了不适
Schrödinger himself writes
薛定谔自己写道
在这里 让人不快
并且显然会被反对的是
使用了虚数
波函数 ψ 根本而言无疑是一个实函数
This seems like a fair objection,
这看起来是一条恰当的反对意见
so why does an imaginary number
所以首先在三次方程解当中出现的虚数
that first appeared in the solution to the cubic
turn up in fundamental physics?
为什么会进入基础物理的方程中呢
Well, it's because of some unique properties
这是因为虚数某些独一无二的性质
of imaginary numbers.
Imaginary numbers exist on a dimension perpendicular
虚数位于与实轴正交的方向上
to the real number line.
Together, they form the complex plane.
两者共同构成了复平面
Watch what happens when we repeatedly multiply by i.
看看我们重复乘以 i 会发生什么
Starting with one.
从 1 开始
One times i is i,
1 × i = 1
i times i is negative one, by definition.
根据定义 i × i = -1
Negative one times i is negative i,
-1 × i = -i
and negative i times i is one.
-i × i = 1
We've come back to where we started,
我们已经回到了开始的地方
and if we keep multiplying by i,
如果我们继续乘以 i
the point will keep rotating around.
复平面上的点就会绕原点转圈
So when you're multiplying by i,
所以做这样的乘法
what you're really doing is rotating
实际上相当于在复平面上转过 90°
by 90 degrees in the complex plane.
Now, there is a function that repeatedly multiplies by i
现在假设有一个函数 沿着 x 轴方向
as you go down the X-axis.
它的值反复地乘以 i
And that is e to the ix.
这就是 e^ix
It creates a spiral by essentially spreading out
它沿着 x 轴伸展
these rotations all along the X-axis.
产生了一条绕 x 轴旋转的螺旋线
If you look at the real part of the spiral,
如果观察这条螺旋线的实部
it's a cosine wave.
这是余弦波
And if you look at the imaginary part, it's a sine wave.
如果你观察虚部 这是正弦波
The two quintessential functions that describe waves
用于描述波动的最典型的两个函数
are both contained in e to the ix.
都被包括在 e^ix 之中
So when Schrodinger goes to write down a wave equation,
所以当薛定谔写下波动方程的时候
he naturally assumes that the solutions to his equation
他自然假设了他的方程的解
will look something like e to the ix,
会取类似 e^ix 的形式
specifically e to the ikx minus omega t.
准确地说 是 e^i(kx-ωt)
You might wonder why he would use that formulation
你也许会问他为什么会用这个公式
and not just a simple sine wave,
而非一个简单的正弦波
but the exponential has some useful properties.
指数函数有些有用的性质
If you take the derivative with respect to position or time,
如果你对上式求关于位置或时间的导数
that derivative is proportional
导函数将
to the original function itself.
正比于原函数本身
And that's not true if you use the sine function
这点对正弦函数并不成立
whose derivative is cosine.
它的导数是余弦函数
Plus, since the Schrodinger equation is linear,
此外 由于薛定谔方程是线性的
you can add together an arbitrary number of solutions
可以将任意多这样的解叠加起来
of this form, creating any sort of wave shape you like,
得到任何你想要的波形
and it too, will be a solution to Schrodinger's equation.
其结果也是薛定谔方程解
The physicist Freeman Dyson later writes,
物理学家弗里曼·戴森随后写道
薛定谔将负一的平方根置入方程
这一切突然有了意义
它马上从一个热传导方程
变成了一个波动方程
而薛定谔不无喜悦地发现
这个方程具有与玻尔原子模型中
量子化轨道相对应的解
这说明薛定谔方程正确地描述了
我们对原子的行为所知道的一切
这是一切化学和许多物理学的根基
方程中负一的平方根
意味着自然凭借复数而非实数来运转
对于薛定谔和其他所有人
这项发现是个彻头彻尾的惊喜
So imaginary numbers
所以虚数
discovered as a quirky, intermediate step
本是作为一个古怪的中间步骤
on the way to solving the cubic
出现在三次方程的解当中
turn out to be fundamental to our description of reality.
却被发现是我们描述现实的基石
Only by giving up maths connection to reality
只有放下数学与现实的关联
could it guide us
我们才能走向
to a deeper truth about the way the universe works.
事关万物运行的深刻真理